For as long as I can remember, I've been told the same thing my whole life.
从我记事起 一生都在被告知同样的事
-Scum. -Bastard.
-废物 -混蛋
Good-for-nothing.
一无是处
I was born and raised in the slums.
我在贫民窟出生、长大
My parents didn't have the time or energy to feed me.
我父母没有时间和精力养我
When I was hungry, I stole, I robbed,
我饿了就去偷、去抢
and did everything but kill.
除了杀人什么都做了
I slept when I wanted to,
我想睡就睡
and woke up when I felt like it.
想醒来的时候就醒来
I was free.
我很自由
Hey! Watch where you're going!
喂！看路啊！
Oh, a vagrant. You piece of scum.
原来是个流浪汉 你这败类
I beg you, please, stop.
我求你了 别打了
That's enough.
够了
Who the hell are you?
你又是谁？
Even if we wander the beach aimlessly,
即使我们漫无目的地在海边走
we'll never spot a current leading out.
也找不到向外的洋流的
This sun and sand are just going to drain us.
这阳光和沙滩只会让我们筋疲力尽
Enough with the logic!
别再用那种逻辑了！
I may be an idiot but I'm trying to do what's best for us.
我也许是个白痴 但我正在努力做对我们最好的事情
The forest is full of bugs and monsters, right?
那个森林充满了虫子和怪物对吧？
But together, we can beat them.
但只要我们团结 就能打败它们
Knowing that you are a girl, I want to avoid such danger.
知道你是女生 我才想避免这样的危险
Please, be my husband after all!
拜托 请成为我的丈夫吧
It's too soon for that.
说这个还太早吧
First, we need to get out of here alive. Then you can think about marriage.
首先 我们得活着出去 然后你才能考虑婚姻
Let's take our time and come up with a safe strategy.
我们慢慢来 想出一个安全的策略
Combat is to be studiously avoided.
应该彻底避免战斗
You're very discreet. That'll make a good husband.
你很谨慎 你一定能成为一个好丈夫
Wh… Who are you? Did you just come from the sky?
你…你是谁？ 你刚才是从天而降的吗？
There was so much commotion in the forest.
森林里太多骚动了
That is unusual.
那很不正常
I saw many Soshin corpses.
我看到了许多宗慎尸体
Which is also unusual.
那也很不正常
Did you guys do this?
是你们干的吗？
It's turned into a man.
它变成了男人
It's a monster! Run!
它是个怪物！快跑！
Why do you run?
你们为什么要跑？
It's useless.
没用的
I don't mind, but… doesn't it make you curious?
我不介意 但是你们不觉得好奇吗？
When something is out of the ordinary,
出现不寻常的事时
I don't like it.
我不喜欢
Wow… you move around a lot, for a human.
作为人类而言 你很能跑啊
You're swift too. For a human.
作为人类而言 你速度也很快
Nurugai!
濡亥！
Run on my signal!
我给你信号你就跑
Don't think about defeating it, just run!
不要想着打败它 跑就行了！
I may not have stamina but…
我也许没有耐力 但是…
no one can beat my swordplay speed!
我的剑速无人能及！
Now!
快跑！
My clothes are torn.
我的衣服都破了
This is awful.
太糟糕了
M… Master!
师…师父！
Run! Tenza!
典坐！快跑！
Yes, sir!
是！
Who was that?
那是谁？
He's Yamada Asaemon Shion, my teacher!
他是山田浅右卫门士远 我的师父！
He's lost his eyesight,
他失去了视力
but he's running through the forest.
但他正在穿越森林
He can "see" through smell and sounds.
他能通过味道和声音来“看到”东西
We're far from it now.
我们现在离它很远了
Mister Nurugai… I mean Miss.
濡亥先生…我是说小姐
With my teacher here, there's no need to worry.
我师父在这里 没什么可担心的
Lord Shion is my savior and a master swordsman!
士远大人是我的救命恩人 他是一位剑圣！
He's an amazing person!
他是一个了不起的人！
About your swordplay…
关于你的剑术
Too focused on speed, so your technique is sloppy.
过于注重速度 所以你的技能变差了
You need to aim for the neck or legs first.
你需要首先瞄准颈部或腿部
And I could hear your messy footwork.
我能听到你凌乱的步法
Every strike must be executed with great care.
每一击都必须小心执行
Even at a time like this, you're still a teacher, aren't you?
即使在这样的时刻 你依然是老师 是吧？
I'm actually kind of relieved.
其实我有点松了口气
Your carelessness can't be fixed either.
你的粗心也是改不了
Still…
不过
Glad you're safe. I thought I'd seen the last of you on the ship.
看到你安全我还是很高兴 我以为在船上是最后一次见到你了
You're full of wit.
你充满了智慧
What are you doing here out alone, sir?
老师一个人在外面做什么？
I had finished my duty and I was heading to return.
我已经完成了任务 正准备返回
I couldn't find any ocean currents off the island,
我找不到任何离岛的洋流
so I was searching around.
所以我就在附近寻找
Just like us.
跟我们一样
There was one spot that looked like it had an outgoing current.
有一个地方看起来好像有向外的洋流
But…
但是
I've never heard such a sound or presence.
我从没听过这样的声音
I'm blind, so I have my limits.
我是个盲人 有我的局限性
I was looking for someone to return with me.
我在找人跟我一起回去
Please, take us there!
拜托 带我们去那里吧！
The three of us can make it work!
我们三个人一起一定能成功！
Perhaps we can.
我们也许可以
But before that…
但在那之前…
What are you doing… Master?
你在做什么 师父？
It's your turn to explain.
轮到你来解释了
Why are you protecting a sinner?
你为什么要保护一个罪人？
If there's a rule violation or something unexpected,
如果有违反规则或意外情况
you'll be told to execute the sinner immediately.
你应该立刻处决罪人
That is what I did.
我就是这么做的
I killed the sinner who tried to seduce me.
我杀死了试图勾引我的罪人
I did it the least painful way possible.
我使用了最不痛苦的方式
You seem to have a soft spot for that sinner.
你似乎对那个罪人情有独钟
Tell me the reason.
告诉我理由
Depending on that, I will execute them myself.
根据你说的 我会亲自处决他们
This child… has not committed any crime.
这个孩子没犯任何罪
The contents of the sinners' profiles are all in my head.
罪人档案内容都在我的脑海里
I'm well aware of their backgrounds.
我非常清楚他们的背景
But a crime is…
但犯罪是
decided by the era we live in, Tenza.
由我们生活的时代决定的 典坐
We, the Yamada Asaemon are swords for this era to wield.
我们山田浅右卫门是这个时代的利剑
It is out of order for a sword to choose who it cuts.
由剑来选择砍谁是不妥的
Above all, if you break the rules, it could
最重要的是 如果你破坏规矩
be seen as a rebellion against the entire Yamada Clan.
会被看成对整个山田家的背叛
One man's actions can endanger the entire clan.
一个人的行为能危及整个族群
But, you taught me how to use the sword, Master.
但是 师父教会了我如何使用剑
I was a self-reliant wanderer.
我是一个自力更生的流浪者
You had no obligation to take me in,
你没有义务接纳我
but you did, Master.
但是你这么做了 师父
That's because I saw talent and potential in you.
那是因为我看到了你的天赋和潜力
I can say the same too!
我也能说同样的话！
I see potential in a world
我看到了这孩子
where this child can live freely!
可以自由生活的世界的潜力！
Those are some wise words.
这是一些明智的话
I learned from you!
是从老师身上学来的
Also, I know that you are a kind man.
另外 我知道你是一个善良的人
I knew you would listen if I spoke from my heart.
我知道如果我说心里话 你会听的
Helping others? I don't get it.
帮助别人？我不明白
Well, if you insist that much.
好吧 如果你这么坚持的话
I knew it!
我就知道！
See! He's a good person after all!
看！我就说他是个好人吧！
Right…
是的
I'll allow it for now, but…
我暂时允许 但是
If protecting her puts the Yamada Clan
如果保护她让山田家族
or you in danger…
或者你陷入危险…
Then at that time, I will…
到了那个时候 我会…
-What is it? -How did you know?
-怎么了？ -你怎么知道
That she was a girl?
她是个女孩？
It's obvious. I have an eye for these kind of things.
很明显 对于那种事我眼力很好
You really do like those kind of jokes.
你真的很喜欢那种笑话
Pleased to meet you, Master.
很高兴认识你 师父
Pleased to meet you, too, Nurugai.
我也很高兴认识你 濡亥
But there is no need for you to call me Master.
那你没必要叫我师父
I haven't taught you anything yet.
我什么都还没有教你
All right! Let's go to the ocean currents you mentioned!
好了！我们现在去你说过的洋流吧！
Keep it down.
小声一点
Do this carefully, no rush.
仔细一点 不要着急
The danger at hand is that monster from earlier.
眼前的危险是之前的那个怪物
It's hard to believe it's human.
很难相信那是人类
Let's think about what to do when we encounter it.
我们想想遇到它后要怎么做吧
If we're going to run from it, we can just do like we did before.
如果我们要逃避它 我们可以像之前那样做
It seems I've been taken for a fool.
看来我被当成傻子了
You're a life saver, Master.
师父 你真是救命恩人
Thanks.
谢谢
Master!
师父！
Huh? I thought I sliced off your head.
嗯？我以为我砍下了你的头
You're pretty tough.
你还真结实
Take that!
看招！
I'm used to that already.
我已经习惯了
The truth is, you won't become "tan" unless you're alive.
事实是 除非你活着 否则你无法变成“棕褐色”
But you piss me off, so die.
但你惹我生气了 所以去死吧
What should we do? Should we run?
我们该怎么做？我们要跑吗？
No, I have to fight.
不 我必须战斗
One Cut Secret Technique…
一刀秘术…
Wait, Ten--
等一下 典…
Roaring Rain!
咆哮之雨！
I told you that I'm used to this.
我告诉过你我已经习惯了
Tenza!
典坐！
Hey Master, why did ya take in some punk kid like me?
师父 你为什么要收留 像我这样的小混混？
Try asking more properly.
你好好问一遍
Why did ya take me in?
为什么要收留我？
Our job is to end lives.
我们的工作是终结生命
So I prefer to spend the rest of my time helping others.
所以我希望在其他时间里帮助别人
Well, at times you can be a little rough.
好吧 有时候你比较粗鲁
But at your core, I see potential.
但在你的核心 我看到了潜力
Are you a saint?
你是个圣人吗？
Helping others? I don't get it.
帮助别人？我不明白
Take that!
看招！
Dammit!
该死！
Your swordplay is sloppy. You're too driven by emotion.
你的剑法草率 你太情绪化了
I can sense anger and… hesitation.
我能感觉到愤怒和迟疑
It's not like I want to be a samurai.
我又没有想成为武士
This is all pointless.
这些都没有意义
I'm not asking you to be a samurai from the start.
我没有要你一开始就成为武士
But if one day… you have something to protect,
但如果有一天 你有想要保护的东西
I'm sure the sword you've trained with will help you.
我确定你训练过的剑会帮助你
Something to protect?
想要保护的东西？
Look at that cherry blossom tree.
看看那颗樱花树
The trunk is thin and the flowers are still buds.
树干还很细 花朵仍含苞待放
But a bud has all kinds of potential.
但那些花苞有各种潜力
Just like you.
就像你一样
The time will surely come when this bud of potential blossoms.
有潜力的花苞开放的时候一定会到来
-Scum. -Bastard.
-废物 -混蛋
-Good-for-nothing. -Vagrant.
-一无是处 -流浪汉
Okay, let's continue.
好吧 我们继续
I don't have any…
我没有
possibilities. None!
任何可能 没有！
I have no identity nor money!
我没有身份 也没有钱！
From the day I was born, I've had no potential!
从我出生的那天起 我就没有潜力！
-I quit. -What?
-我不干了 -什么？
I said I quit!
我说我不干了！
I'm tired of this rigid lifestyle!
我受够了这种死板的生活方式！
I'm going to live how I want!
我要随心所欲地生活
-Are you serious? -Damn right!
-你是认真的吗？ -是啊！
Then, I have one condition.
那么 有一个条件
One condition?
条件？
Beat me just once.
打败我一次
It can be any time and day.
可以是任何时候
When you do, I'll allow you to quit.
如果你做到了 我就让你退出
I don't have time for this.
我没时间做那些
Where are you going? The dojo is on the other side.
你要去哪里？道场在另一边
Shion has told me about you.
士远跟我说了你的事
Were you able to beat him?
你能打败他吗？
Are you trying to take me back?
你是想带我回去吗？
Do what you want.
做你想做的
But, at least join me on a walk.
但是 起码跟我散个步吧
I woke up early and have nothing to do.
我早起没什么事做
TAKE REFUGE IN AMIDA BUTSU
（南无阿弥陀佛）
The one who rests here is…
长眠于此的人
the man who used to be Shion's disciple.
曾经是士远的徒弟
His name was Tesshin.
他的名字是铁心
A disciple?
徒弟？
Like you, he was a man of bad behavior.
跟你一样 他也品行不端
He had the talent, but lacked will power.
他有天赋 但缺乏意志力
I'm sure Master gave him a hard time then?
我想师父一定让他不好过吧？
Just like me.
就跟我一样
Back then, Shion was obsessed with improving his skills.
那时候 士远痴迷于提高自己的技能
He wasn't as eager to teach as he is now.
他不像现在这样热衷于教学
Eventually, Tesshin said "I'll live my life the way I want to,"
最终 铁心说 “我要过我想过的生活”
and he left the dojo.
然后离开了道场
For a while, nothing changed.
有一段时间 什么都没有改变
That day was the same as usual.
那是平常的一天
Shion went out to do his job.
士远出门去工作
He stood in front of the sinner.
他站在罪人面前
Shion raised his sword,
士远举起他的剑
but he couldn't bring it down.
但他无法挥下去
Do you mean that…
你是说…
Yes. Shion realized that,
是的 士远意识到了
the sinner in front of him was Tesshin.
他面前的罪人正是铁心
After Tesshin left the dojo,
铁心离开道场后
he soon found it hard to make ends meet, so he began committing crimes.
很快发现自己入不敷出 于是他开始犯罪
What did Master do?
师父是怎么做的？
He cut him, of course. As a Yamada Asaemon.
很显然 他砍了他 作为一个山田浅右卫门
Shion clearly heard Tesshin's last words.
士远清楚地听到了铁心的遗言
He said to him,
他对他说…
"I'm sorry, Master."
“对不起 师父”
After that,
在那以后
Shion became passionate about teaching his younger disciples
士远开始热衷于教导他的年轻弟子
and started helping others.
并开始帮助他人
If you live your life as an outlaw,
如果你过着亡命之徒的生活
you might eventually end up like him.
你的结局也许会像他一样
Shion doesn't want you to go down that same path.
士远不想让你走同样的路
Just like you. The time will surely come when this bud of potential blossoms.
就像你一样 有潜力的花苞开放的时候一定会到来
What are you going to do?
你要怎么做？
Are you going to walk away without beating him once?
你打算不打败他一次 直接走人吗？
Tenzaka.
典坐
Master, I want you to train with me.
师父 我想让你训练我
Oh, it looks like you are not the man you were.
你看起来像换了个人一样
I've never been serious about anything until now. But…
在这之前 我从没有对任何事认真过 但是…
Your defense is weak!
你的防守很弱
Once more!
再一次！
Again!
再来！
Keep it going!
继续！
I want to beat him at least once.
我想至少打败他一次
This man was the first to believe in my potential.
这个人是第一个相信我潜力的人
Hey, Master…
师父
Do you think I can believe in my own potential?
你觉得我能相信自己的潜力吗？
And as you once said to me… I wonder if…
你就像跟我说过的那样…我在想…
I wonder if I'll ever have someone I want to protect.
我在想我是否会有想要保护的人
My fingertips are getting cold…
我的指尖开始变凉了
But from the chest up,
但是胸口以上
it feels burning hot.
觉得很烫
Oh, I see…
我明白了
Am I going to die?
我是要死了吗？
Is everyone going to die here?
所有人都会死在这里吗？
Are we all going to be killed by this monster?
我们都会被这怪物杀死吗？
I won't let you!
我不会让你得逞的！
Even if I die, I'll make sure the other two get away!
即使我死了 我也要保证另外两个人逃脱
I'll do whatever it takes!
我会不惜一切代价
I'll give all I have to buy them time!
我会竭尽全力为他们争取时间！
Don't come over here.
不要过来
Run! Please, get out of here.
快跑 离开这里
Please, run, you two.
你们两个 拜托 快跑
No, Master. You can't win.
不 师父 你赢不了的
You know it, don't you?
你知道的 对吧？
It got my throat. I can't even speak.
已经到了我的喉咙 我说不出话了
Master, please, just run!
师父 拜托 快跑
Please, let me say… one word.
拜托 让我说一句话
Tenzo! No!
典坐！不！
Master, I'm sorry. After all you have done for me.
师父 对不起 你为我做了这么多事
Nurugai, please, live. You have potential.
濡亥 请你活下去 你有潜力
Potential… I wonder what kind I might've had?
潜力 我想知道 我拥有的是哪种潜力？
So persistent.
如此执着
Why did you abandon him? I'm going back!
你为什么要抛弃他？我要回去！
Th… This is what Tenza wanted.
这是典坐想要的
But you're his teacher, aren't you?
但你是他的老师 不是吗？
-And he's your disciple, right? -That's why!
-他是你的徒弟 对吗？ -这就是为什么！
We are comrades with the same resolve.
我们是志同道合的战友
What he did for us
他为我们做的事
must not go to waste.
绝不能浪费了
We can't beat that thing now.
我们现在打不过那个东西
We would have all been dead. We had to pull out.
如果不是他 我们就都死了 我们不得不撤退
But I promise,
但我保证
we will make it pay!
我们会让它付出代价！
Yes, I beat you!
太好了！我打败你了！
Good job. Now, you can do as you like.
干得好 现在你能过你想要的生活了
Master, please, continue to teach me…
师父 请继续教我吧
I mean… Master, please, continue to teach me the way of the sword,
我是说 师父 请继续教我剑道
I beg you!
求你了！
Of course.
当然可以
Subtitle translation by: Mel Nishi
字幕翻译：朱未耒